# **Shusen Wang**

Postdoctoral Scholar, Department of Statistics and RISELab, UC Berkeley

Phone: (510)229-0382 Email: shusen@berkeley.edu Homepage: wangshusen.github.io

### Research

**Keywords** Machine learning, randomized linear algebra, convex optimization, big data, dis-

tributed computing.

**Summary** I am most interested in computational methods for machine learning. The goal

of my research is making large-scale machine learning, matrix computation, and optimization more efficient. My thesis work is randomized algorithms for speeding up machine learning and matrix computation with loss of a limited amount of accuracy. My postdoctoral work at Berkeley is mainly large-scale machine learning,

optimization, and data analysis via distributed computing.

### Education

**2011-2016 Doctor of Engineering**; Zhejiang University (Hangzhou, China)

Major: Computer Science

Advisor: Zhihua Zhang

Thesis: Large-Scale Machine Learning: A Randomized Approach and Theoretical

Analysis

**2007-2011** Bachelor of Engineering; Zhejiang University (Hangzhou, China)

Major: Computer Science

# Work Experience

**2016-Now Postdoctoral Scholar**; Department of Statistics, UC Berkeley, CA, USA)

Advisor: Michael W. Mahoney

Research: randomized linear algebra and implementation

**2014-2015** Research Intern; Baidu Big Data Lab (Beijing, China)

Mentor: Tong Zhang

Research: optimization algorithms

**2012** Research Intern; Google Research (Beijing, China)

Research: randomized algorithms

**2011-2012** Intern; Microsoft Research Asia (Beijing, China)

Mentors: Haixun Wang and Yangqiu Song

### Academic Service

#### • Journal Reviewer

- Journal of Machine Learning Research 2015, 2016, 2017
- SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing, 2017
- ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software, 2017
- Journal of Econometrics, 2017
- SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications, 2017

#### Conference Reviewer or Committee Member

- NIPS 2014, 2015, 2017
- ICML 2017, 2018
- IJCAI 2015, 2017, 2018
- AAAI 2016, 2018

### Selected Honors & Awards

2014	Baidu Scholarship, awarded to 8 Chinese students in the world, US\$30,000
2013	Microsoft Research Asia Fellow, awarded to 10 students in Asia Pacific, US\$10,000
2012	Scholarship Award for Excellent Doctoral Student Granted by Ministry of Education, $\text{US}\$5,\!000$
2012-2014	National Scholarship for Graduate Students, 3 times, each time US\$5,000

# Journal Papers

- Scalable Kernel K-Means Clustering with Nystrom Approximation: Relative-Error Bounds.
  Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. Accepted by Journal of Machine Learning Research conditioned on minor revisions; available at arXiv:1706.02803, 2017.
- Towards More Efficient SPSD Matrix Approximation and CUR Matrix Decomposition. Shusen Wang, Zhihua Zhang, and Tong Zhang. *Journal of Machine Learning Research*, 17(210):1–49, 2016. (JMLR 2016).
- SPSD Matrix Approximation vis Column Selection: Theories, Algorithms, and Extensions. Shusen Wang, Luo Luo, and Zhihua Zhang. *Journal of Machine Learning Research*, 17(49):1-49, 2016. (JMLR 2016).
- Improving CUR Matrix Decomposition and the Nystrom Approximation via Adaptive Sampling. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 14: 2729-2769, 2013. (JMLR 2013).
- EP-GIG Priors and Applications in Bayesian Sparse Learning. Zhihua Zhang, Shusen Wang, Dehua Liu, and Michael I. Jordan. *Journal of Machine Learning Research*, 13: 2031-2061, 2012. (JMLR 2012).

## ----- Preprints

- GIANT: Globally Improved Approximate Newton Method for Distributed Optimization. Shusen
  Wang, Farbod Roosta-Khorasani, Peng Xu, and Michael W. Mahoney. arXiv:1709.03528, 2017.
- A Bootstrap Method for Error Estimation in Randomized Matrix Multiplication. Miles E. Lopes, Shusen Wang, Michael W. Mahoney. Under the review of *Journal of Machine Learning Research*; available at *arXiv:1708.01945*, 2017.
- Sketched Ridge Regression: Optimization Perspective, Statistical Perspective, and Model Averaging. Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. Under the review of *Journal* of Machine Learning Research; a short version is published in ICML 2017.
- Improved Analyses of the Randomized Power Method and Block Lanczos Method. Shusen Wang, Zhihua Zhang, and Tong Zhang. arXiv:1508.06429, 2015.

# Conference Papers

- Sketched Ridge Regression: Optimization Perspective, Statistical Perspective, and Model Averaging. Shusen Wang, Alex Gittens, and Michael W. Mahoney. In *International Conference* on Machine Learning, 2017. (ICML 2017).
- Towards Real-Time Geologic Feature Detection from Seismic Measurements using a Randomized Machine-Learning Algorithm. Youzuo Lin, Shusen Wang, Jayaraman Thiagarajan, George Guthrie, and David Coblentz. In Proceeding of Society of Exploration Geophysics (SEG), 2017.
- Open Domain Short Text Conceptualization: A Generative + Descriptive Modeling Approach.
  Yangqiu Song, Shusen Wang, and Haixun Wang. In International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 2015. (IJCAI 2015).
- Improving the Modified Nystrom Method Using Spectral Shifting. Shusen Wang, Chao Zhang, Hui Qian, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 20th ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, 2014. (KDD 2014).
- Efficient Algorithms and Error Analysis for the Modified Nystrom Method. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In *Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, JMLR W&CP*, 2014. (AISTATS 2014).
- Making Fisher Discriminant Analysis Scalable. Bojun Tu, Zhihua Zhang, Shusen Wang, and Hui Qian. In the International Conference on Machine Learning. (ICML 2014).
- Exact Subspace Clustering in Linear Time. Shusen Wang, Bojun Tu, Congfu Xu, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 28th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. (AAAI 2014).
- Using The Matrix Ridge Approximation to Speedup Determinantal Point Processes Sampling Algorithms. Shusen Wang, Chao Zhang, Hui Qian, and Zhihua Zhang. In the 28th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. (AAAI 2014).
- Transfer Understanding from Head Queries to Tail Queries. Yangqiu Song, Haixun Wang, Weizhu Chen, and Shusen Wang. In the 23rd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management. (CIKM 2014).
- Nonconvex Relaxation Approaches to Robust Matrix Recovery. Shusen Wang, Dehua Liu, and Zhihua Zhang. In *International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence*. (IJCAI 2013).
- A Scalable CUR Matrix Decomposition Algorithm: Lower Time Complexity and Tighter Bound. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 25. (NIPS 2012).

- Colorization by Matrix Completion. Shusen Wang and Zhihua Zhang. In the 26th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. (AAAI 2012).
- Efficient Subspace Segmentation via Quadratic Programming. Shusen Wang, Xiaotong Yuan, Tiansheng Yao, Shuicheng Yan, and Jialie Shen. In the 25th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. (AAAI 2011).